Raymond Gloeckler
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Raymond Gloeckler papers
1952-2008
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Gloeckler, Raymond
1.4 linear feet
The papers of Wisconsin printmaker and educator Raymond Gloeckler measure 1.4 linear feet and date from 1952 to 2008. Gloeckler's career is documented through biographical material, correspondence with galleries and art organizations, exhibition and commission files, printed material, and artwork.
Provenance
The papers were donated in 2010 by Raymond Gloeckler.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Raymond Gloeckler (1928- ) is a printmaker and educator in Madison, Wisconsin. Gloeckler was born on December 13, 1928 in Portage, Wisconsin. He attended the University of Wisconsin, Madison, receiving his B.S. in 1950 and his M.S. in 1952. After holding several teaching positions at colleges in Michigan, he returned to the University of Wisconsin, Madison, in 1961 as a professor and taught there until his retirement in 1993. Gloeckler established himself as a leading figure in 20th-century woodcuts and wood engraving, exhibiting his works nationally and internationally, and receiving numerous awards.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Wisconsin printmaker and educator Raymond Gloeckler measure 1.4 linear feet and date from 1952 to 2008. Gloeckler's career as an artist is documented through biographical material, correspondence with galleries and art organizations, exhibition and commission files, printed material, and artwork.
Biographical material includes a professional application, award certificates, and biographical documentation compiled for the book Progressive Printmakers: Wisconsin Artists and the Print Renaissance. The bulk of Gloeckler's correspondence consists of handmade holiday and greeting cards sent to him from friends and fellow printmakers including Warrington Colescott, Rosemary Feit Covey, Arthur Geisert, William Haendel, Mary Meyer, and David Rynning. Also found is scattered correspondence regarding the sale and exhibition of his work. Exhibition and commission files only document select projects and may include notes, correspondence, exhibition lists, and agreements. Printed material consists chronological files containing newspaper and magazine clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, newsletters, university publications, and brochures. Also found are three limited edition books containing prints by Gloeckler. This collection also contains two pencil drawings and four holiday prints by Gloeckler.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1959, circa 1993-1999 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1962-2005 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Exhibition and Commission Files, 1959-1994 (Box 1; 9 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1952-2008 (Box 1-2; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1980-2004 (Box 2; 3 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Printmakers--Wisconsin; Educators--Wisconsin
Types of Materials:
Greeting cards; Drawings; Notes; Awards
Names:
Colescott, Warrington, 1921-; Covey, Rosemary Feit, 1954-; Geisert, Arthur; Haendel, William; Rynning, David
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1959, circa 1993-1999, Series 1:; (Box 1; 5 folders)
  Found here are award certificates and an application for promotion which contains details of Raymond Gloeckler's professional activities up to 1959. Also included are various biographical materials compiled for Progressive Printmakers: Wisconsin Artists and the Print Renaissance. Within these files are biographical notes, slides, lists of prints by Gloeckler, excerpts from a 1993 interview, artist statements, correspondence regarding the publication, and draft text.
  - Application for Promotion, Eastern Michigan University, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Material compiled for Progressive Printmakers: Wisconsin Artists and the Print Renaissance, circa 1993-1999, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
- Correspondence, 1962-2005, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
  Gloeckler's correspondence is with the Butler Institute of Art, Cincinnati Art Museum, and other galleries and art organizations. Letters primarily concern the sale or exhibiton of his prints. Also found within the general correspondence are a few letters from friends. The bulk of this series consists of handmade holiday and greeting cards sent to Gloeckler from friends and fellow printmakers including Warrington Colescott, Rosemary Feit Covey, Arthur Geisert, William Haendel, Mary Meyer, David Rynning, and others.
  Holiday and greeting cards are arranged in alphabetical order followed by a folder of cards from unidentified senders.
  - Correspondence with Butler Institute of American Art, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Cincinnati Art Museum, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1962-2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Holiday and Greeting Cards, 1979-2004, (17 folders) (Box 1, Folder 9-25)
- Exhibition and Commission Files, 1959-1994, Series 3:; (Box 1; 9 folders)
  Found here are commission and exhibition files maintained by Gloeckler for select projects. Within these files may be notes, correspondence, exhibition lists, agreements, and printed material. Of note is a file of correspondence, lists of artwork, and other details regarding his 1980 retrospective exhibition at the Milwaukee Art Center.
  - Commission, Barbarian Press, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Commission, St. Mary's Congregation, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Commission, Wisconsin Arts Foundation, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Exhibitions, British Society of Wood Engravers, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Exhibitions, Garelick's Gallery, 1961-1971, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 30-32)
  - Exhibition, Milwaukee Art Center, Raymond Gloeckler: A Retrospective, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition, The Print Club, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Printed Material, 1952-2008, Series 4:; (Box 1-2; 0.7 linear feet)
  Printed material includes three limited edition books containing prints by Gloeckler and two books of poetry by Dik Schwanke. Also found are chronological files containing various printed material kept by Gloeckler to document his professional activities. These files include newspaper and magazine clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, newsletters, university publications, and brochures.
  - Books, Everyday Stuff and or am i so strange by Dik Schwanke, 1972, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Book, The Horny-Goloch, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Book, Raymond Gloeckler: The Engravers Cut, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Book, Snippets by N. F. Simpson, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Catalog, People Reading: Selections from the Collection of Donald and Patricia Oresman, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Chronological Printed Material, 1952, 1955-1967, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 40-45)
  - Chronological Printed Material, 1968-1996, (9 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Printed Material regarding Barry Moser, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Artwork, circa 1980-2004, Series 5:; (Box 2; 3 folders)
  This series contains two pencil drawings by Gloeckler, four holiday prints created by Gloeckler, and three wood engravings by Earl Nitschke, printed by the Enigma Press.
  - Pencil Drawings by Raymond Gloeckler, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Holiday Prints by Raymond Gloeckler, 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wood Engravings by Earl Nitschke, circa 2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)